{
  "reference_number": "12479",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "In fact, I would strongly urge the government aims to get to carbon zero by 2040. We need to cut emissions fast and demonstrate a\n real commitment to the goal of staying below 1.5 degrees global temperature rise. Seeking advice from the Climate Commission,\n\n especially on how to achieve the target as efficiently and equitably as possible, is appropriate."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Long-Lived Gases and Stabilised Short-Lived Gases - Long-lived gases to net zero by 2050 while also stabilising short-lived gases",
      "answer_index": 12,
      "notes": "A shorter time frame of 2040 is desirable."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "NZ's record with international carbon credits has been deeply troubling. Purchasing international carbon units cannot be a substitute\n\n for reducing domestic emissions. It is critical to bring gross domestic emissions across transport, energy and electricity sectors to\n zero. In addition, separately from these domestic efforts, NZ can certainly purchase carefully vetted international carbon credits to\n support global mitigation efforts. It is important to ensure that there should be close monitoring of cumulative emissions. NZ should\n\n also significantly strengthen its commitments under the Paris Agreement."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "In exceptional circumstances, such as changes in technology and scientific knowledge, it may be appropriate to allow the target to\n be revised."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Allowing frequent changes of budget can create uncertainty."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "In addition to the considerations specified, it is essential that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account\nindigenous, traditional and local knowledges."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "A strict timeframe is essential."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Government policies and plans should have at their heart a commitment to: environmental, social and economic sustainability; intra-\nand inter-generational equity; Te Tiriti o Waitangi; and principles of social and cultural inclusion. This would mean working not only with\n\nscientific experts but also with social scientists, environmental and social NGOs, and with communities who need to be part of the\nconversation about the creation and shape of budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission should not have decision making authority. This is the role of government/elected officials. All\nreports of the Commission should be tabled in Parliament to ensure transparency and accountability."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Note that the category of 'climate and environmental science' should include social science. By way of comparison, one of the most\nsignificant criticisms of the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change has been the domination of natural/physical scientists with a\n\ntechnocratic focus. This is now being addressed. It would be good to see the NZ Climate Commission include social scientists with\nknowledge of issues of gender, culture, equity and justice in the context of climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, this is essential. Any meaningful action plan must address both mitigation and adaptation."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "I strongly support the provisions to prepare a national climate risk assessment, as well as a national adaptation plan with regular\nreview and reporting on this.The current practice of expecting regional councils to come up with their own plans is inadequate -\nnational-level plans are required. The idea of adaptation reporting power seems like a useful tool and having it mandatory through\n\nembedding it in legislation seems appropriate. Yes, there will be administrative and compliance costs - but if monitored and reviewed\nregularly, there should be evidence as to whether it is helpful in meeting the goals."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "This is an exciting and important moment, This Bill is of such importance to the country (and to the global effort to address climate\n\nchange) that it gives hope of a better future not just for our generation but the generations to come. In order to ensure its success, it\nis essential that continued and more creative forms of public engagement throughout the process be sought by the government."
    }
  ]
}
